[Music]
hi I'm Jennifer from shabby Fabrics I'm
so excited to show you how to make this
Bible cover I know when I'm off to
church in the middle of the winter in
the rainy season I don't want my Bible
to get wet so making one of these covers
is perfect to just protect it now I know
people's bibles are different sizes be
sure to go to the shabby Fabric's
homepage on the very bottom there's a
link called free downloads click there
the Bible project the Bible cover
project will be there and it'll show you
how to measure your Bible so you can
make the cover fit your specific book
let me show you how quick fun and easy
it is to make this and it makes a great
gift it really makes a wonderful gift
now you'll need some Fabrics of course
uh to complete the project you have a
lining Fabric and interfacing we used a
medium weight interfacing or you can use
a heavier weight maybe a Decor Bond it
just depends on how stiff you want the
cover to be an outer Fabric and some
usable fleece of course you'll have your
handles the cover Pockets Loop some
shabby shapes I'll show you what we did
with this this is really
cute rather than just having a ribbon
Mark the uh page show you what we
did we just used a Shabby shape and we
iron that to either side of the ribbon
so it's a heart there marking the page
and I love that touch it's a great way
to uh just have something even a little
more sweeter um added to the project
um and again just a little more um
interfacing for the the uh handles to
give them a little bit of a little more
stiffness so let's get started this I
can't believe how fast and easy this is
you're going to be surprised first thing
that we're going to do I'll put this
aside for now as we're going to get that
outer Fabric and our fusible fleece you
can go ahead and cut both of those out
and fuse the fusible fleece to the back
of the outer fabric now now you'll be
wanting to use a u probably the friction
pen that's what we used because you can
it'll iron away so let's just pretend
that that's all ironed together at this
point I've got my friction pen and we
just quilted diagonal lines so you can
just start
anywhere just well let's see I want to
go from here to there let's just go
ahead and we can just draw and we did 2
in over from
that and we just kept going and we did
the same thing going this direction and
then we stitched with a coordinating
thread now the neat thing and you know
you probably know what I'm going to do
if you watched any of my other
videos all you need to do to remove the
friction pen is just iron it and it
disappears so I want to show you the
quilt how it looks quilted with the
lines ahead of time so you see there's
that on the back it's even easier to see
it on the back um with regard to the
coordinating thread this is the
Masterpiece from Superior we have the
color card 75 colors there might even be
more colors coming in the future but
gosh it seems like there's always
something that'll match our project I
think we're using today the uh color 142
or 169 if you're choosing this
collection to make your Bible
cover but you can see as I'm ironing
that friction pen is just gone so love
that very convenient um to have to mark
with and not be right that it'll dis you
know that that's going to completely
disappear so that's ready to go the next
thing will be your lining
fabric now with the lining fabric we
chose an interfacing
here and there are fusible interfacing
so you might want to choose that or you
can just Stitch around an eighth of an
inch and secure the front to the back so
that's another option for you I love
fusible interfacings just because
everything's then steady and I don't
have pins everywhere so the first thing
that we'll do to put the Bible cover
together let me just get an example out
here to show you that way it's a lot
easier for you to follow along if you're
seeing an example okay let's put this
aside this is the lining and the
interfacing these are the let me show it
to you on the book it's going to make a
lot more sense if you're seeing it these
are the actual flaps that the book
slides into we use the blue here we've
got a
green so you'll take these and just
simply fold in half and give it a
press pretty
straightforward and you'll do the same
with the other side and you're just
going to position that oh I pressed it
the wrong way I'm like that's not long
enough press the other direction and
that flap of course make the rounded
here and you'll do the same thing on
that side so let me put this
aside so let's get this one
out you'll go
ahead and you'll put those Flaps in fact
Let me let me press that one real good
and
flat okay so that's ready to go as far
as your handles will need to come in
next as well as your
bookmark and the little Loop that has
the button so what you'll be doing with
that you'll take these are your handles
now you're going to take this to the
pressing
mat you're going to fold in half and
give this a press and you'll be able you
you'll be creating a crease of
course so what you'll do is open this
up press toward that crease all the way
down and do the same on the other side
side okay you'll just create fold
again like this and then you're just
going to fold that whole thing in half
and you'll press now we cut some strips
of the
fusible uh
fleece ahead of time and that's just to
give that a little oomph in those
handles so there's a little more to hang
on to so you'll just open that up tuck
in some of that fusible fleece like this
this and you'll just take this to the
sewing machine and you're just going to
stitch an eighth of an inch on this side
and I like to stitch eighth of an inch
on both sides it just gives it it looks
great it just really stabilizes the uh
fusible fleece that's inside there
that's what they look like once they're
sewn together so I have two of those
prepared ahead of time just to save us
some
time and you'll do the same method for
the actual little Loop of for the button
fold in half press press fold in half
now for this one we didn't use a fusible
fleece it's just the fabric and we've
done that ahead of time and again we
just stitched along the one uh side on
this one rather than both sides because
it was so
little so now that you have the lining
and the flaps this is where you want to
line everything up now I'm looking for
that friction pen again because I want
to find the exact middle
and give it just a little bit of a press
here the exact
middle and I'm going to Mark with my
friction pen that spot
okay cuz I want my handle right there
just a little Mark that'll be caught in
the same allowance you don't even need
to remove that
Mark what we'll be doing with the handle
is 2 in I'm going to line this up in
fact with my mat because I've got these
nice little marks so here's my line 2 in
above 2 in
below I'm going to put a pin in
here so that doesn't move make sure you
don't get a Twist in that handle and
then there's my mark 2 in
below
okay we'll repeat that for this side so
there's my mark 2 in again a
pen and 2 in above
of of course whatever you do to the one
side just make the make sure it's the
same on the other
side actually need to put that pin out
there don't
I I need to repin that one so it's good
and secure I don't want anything to
shift when I'm sewing all of this
together so the handles are ready to
go what about that ribbon and that
shabby those shabby shapes now if you've
never used the shabby shapes we have
these in all kinds of shapes in holidays
so it's fun to be able to bring them out
and to use them for things like this um
just to add a sweet little accent so get
your Ribbon I think this is cut
to 8 in you'll just position your
Ribbon like that going straight
up position the other heart on top
just make sure they're stacked right one
exactly on top of the
other you want to take your time on this
step see I I moved mine slightly I want
to make sure that that is going straight
up out of that heart
there there we go don't rush that step
otherwise it's going to be crooked and
it's going to bug you every time you see
it there you go so that's ready to to go
now for
the um this
portion you'll just pin that in place
again I'm just kind of visualizing
that
Center I keep wanting to pin there let's
pin out the top now the last thing
you'll need to do is with your button
Loop um same thing as
before just trim some of that away I
want it to be all tidy here there's my
Center marked I'm just going to go just
on the other side of that and Mark
that just like
that so the handles and the button Loop
and everything's going to the inside so
just keep that in mind now you'll take
this to the sewing machine of course um
what I like to do is kind of get
everything secured before I put the
Quilted part on Top cuz that's a lot to
manage so I recommend that you just go
ahead and go around the whole thing even
though there's really nothing down here
to secure just go around the whole thing
it stabilizes the project an eighth of
an inch just go all the way around that
now let's pretend that we've already
done that of course these pins would be
removed all you would do at that point
is simply take the Quilted
part pin everything together these pins
wouldn't be here cuz everything would
already be stitched down with your E8
inch basting stitch and you're going to
just pin this whole thing together now
this is really important where the
opening is matters because you've got
Loops over here youve got ribbon up here
make sure that your opening is at the
bottom um and leave probably a good you
know 6 8 in cuz it's pretty bulky to
turn it through so let me show you what
that looks like we've done that ahead of
time so there's the Quilted part we've
sewn around the three sides looks like
how big is our opening here about 5 to 6
in I always recommend clipping the
corners cuz there's a lot of bulk in the
corners so go ahead and just clip those
this is my favorite
part let's turn this all the way
through you can see how quick and easy
this is such a great gift for the person
that really has
everything um sometimes hard for me to
think of gifts to to buy someone when
they already you know they go out and
buy whatever it is they they want we're
blessed to be able to do that um and so
this is so great to be able to give
someone a handmade gift and it has so
much utility so I love I love that when
that's the case so we'll keep turning
all the way
through and of course you'd want to get
in there you probably have your favorite
tool in your sewing room where it helps
to get those Corners pushed out whatever
that is I've SE people use bamboo
skewers I've seen people use special um
tools they've bought at the at the
quilting or sewing store push that all
the way out into the corners then all
you need to do is tuck this down a/4 of
an inch tuck this down a/4 of an inch
you'll pin that and then once this is
pushed all the way through you're just
going to go all the way around and top
Stitch an eighth of an inch all the way
around and your Bible cover cover is
finished I hope you enjoyed this DIY
project from shabby Fabrics
[Music]